Minor external bleeding typically comes from small scrapes, shallow cuts, or abrasions
that only affect the top layers of your skin.
Because this type of bleeding is slow, your goal is to get it under control quickly by
using that keyword we just talked about, pressure.
First step is to apply firm pressure to the wound.
If the person is alert, you can actually ask them to hold the pressure themselves while
you take a moment to get your supplies and put on your gloves.
Once the bleeding slows down, you'll want to wash the area thoroughly with soap and
water.
If it is permitted in your setting and the bleeding has stopped, you can apply a bit
of antibiotic ointment and then cover the wound with a clean dressing or a simple adhesive
bandage.
Advise the person to follow up with a healthcare provider if the wound is gaping and might
need stitches, or if they were injured by a dirty object, which could mean they need
a tetanus shot.
Now, let's put those materials we passed out to use.
I want everyone to start by putting on your gloves right now.
Once you have them on, take your first gauze square and place it firmly over the injury
to apply initial pressure.
Once in place, never pull off that initial layer of gauze as it can dislodge the clots
that are starting to form and interrupt the pressure.